[Music]
y' think too small I got Big Dreams you
just starting them way ahead at the end
scenes started reading and dodging all
of the quick sches money like your
[Music]
Spotify this is episode four and our
guest today is Tom codilla Tom and I
know each other in real life and are
even gasp friends um we have been
partners for over five years or so and
um he's a he's a steel attorney uh here
in Denver with me uh he went to see
Boulder and other places before that
that I'll let him weigh in on
and H he's a fantastic fantastic
attorney and sportsman he's constantly
with like man of the cliff didn't you
win man of the cliff just a keg toss
yeah so like tossing a keg um which is a
really the VIN diagram of lawyers and
people who can or are willing to toss a
keg not a great overlap it's just Tom
sitting right there in the middle of
those two circles um and he has a lovely
dog named Kirby what I what I leave out
of that
Tom ah not much you hit the high
points dog training and keg tossing and
proof reading are my personal
triathon is said you're an academic too
you're a speaker you're a sought after
speaker on on legal appreciate that you
are you're you're like an academic so he
um yeah you're you're published a lot in
things about the law um
so Tom and I met for coffee on Monday
and we were uh talking about some of the
deals that we've both worked on um and
then some deals you know we work
together and but not not all of our
clients you know are completely
overlapping so I had some visibility
into some of these deals he was talking
about but I wouldn't know them as well
as him to describe and I was just
generally telling them about our topic
which is hey tell us about a deal that
didn't go through to closing and why not
and what you could do to what you can
extrapolate from that to um maybe you
know get your deal to go to closing or
to realize it's going to fail real soon
and real quick and real cheaply um so
Tom you have an example story for us
take it
away yeah uh well first thanks for
having me this is really fun and uh
hopefully the story resonates with some
of your listeners so the the story of
the deal is we were the buy side on a
private Equity deal trying to acquire a
logistics company logistics company was
in a foreign country and the negotiating
Norms in that foreign country were
completely foreign to me I had no idea
what I was walking into we also didn't
know exactly what the founders had done
before trying to get sold to piss off
their suppliers so we knew that there
were some outstanding debts but of
course those debts are going to be wiped
Away by the acquisition real quick can
can you tell us just generally uh what
foreign country or continent even is it
are we talking Asia Europe South America
this was Israel oh okay very specific
thank you
yeah yeah and uh so obviously no
language barrier but definitely some
cultural differences you know neither
good nor bad just kind of the way things
get done so we had dealt with the
founders and the founders were very
eager to sell we got through the LOI the
price wasn't a big deal but uh in order
for the business to function they had to
have a good working relationship with a
couple of logistics
suppliers and as a result of operating
on a shooring the founders had incurred
massive debts which they slowly paid
down but then got into more debt with
these logistical companies they were
basically a middleman so originally we
thought okay we'll just go in we'll
negotiate with the debt holders and
they'll get something instead of nothing
and that will be sufficient for us to
move towards closing what we didn't know
was that the way that the founders had
dealt with their creditors was so over
and above what we expected that instead
of taking
75 cents in the dollar 80 cents in the
dollar these creditors said we would
rather see this company not get acquired
than give them the satisfaction of
getting paid out this went around and
around I was on the phone with multiple
Logistics suppliers and I heard the same
thing basically we in good faith
extended credit to these Founders for a
number of years they didn't keep their
word now we're not letting them off the
look you pay us 100 cents on the dollar
or it's nothing and we tried a number of
ways to get around this we tried to get
alternative sources of funding we tried
to buy the intellectual property nothing
worked uh it led to some really
interesting interactions with those
creditors because they just had a
different style that I wasn't prepared
for in the US I think at least I'm
biased obviously because I'm I'm in the
US but uh the deal points get brought up
immediately and it's a sign of
professionalism that you're just going
to discuss the deal points and whoever
gets emotional first gets kind of rained
in by their side because you don't want
to kill the
deal that was not so in this case in
this deal the emotions came first and
they were big emotions the negotiations
basically started at brinksmanship and
and the longer the call went on you
started to see oh well maybe we could do
this you maybe we're not going to kill
this deal maybe there's a possibility
I'll go back to so and so and so there
was this almost dance of showing emotion
and taking a hard line before any
negotiation could take place and I just
wasn't prepared for it uh and so I
wondered if this was common and I looked
up different negotiating styles of
different countries and sure enough
super common uh to just have a
completely different negotiation Style
um on the other side of the table if
you're dealing with a foreign country I
just hadn't dealt with it before you
know I dealt with Latin America pretty
um pretty similar to our negotiation
style uh Chinese negotiations were
relatively straightforward a lot more uh
kind of social validation beforehand but
this was something I'd never experienced
so the deal eventually died because we
couldn't get the creditors on board
plain simple and what it would take to
pay them off would have killed the deal
so I think the lesson I took from it was
one get very clear who your Founders are
and how they've treated their key
suppliers the key third party consents
to the deal and two don't assume that
you're going to get creditors to take
anything but 100 cents in the
dollar what did they do to piss off
their credit you know creditors so much
was it you know is that I'm trying to
decide if that's just culturally they're
offended by the thought of having to
Discount what they're owed or they were
so egregious in their mistreatment
of these third parties that they were
like we're done with this we kind of
just would rather see you fizzle out
then even get some more
money I think they did a lot of the
checks in the mail I think they said
yeah we'll make good because they
anticipated on volume coming in when the
volume didn't come in they didn't have
the revenue to pay back as much as they
said they were going to so they were
constantly paying 50% 75% of what they
said they were going to pay and then
they'd have a good month and they'd pay
most of it down but then they keep some
for capital reserve instead of fully
paying off their creditors so it was I
think an escalating series of broken
promises that were backed by from what I
could tell a good faith belief on the
part of the founders that the business
would come in the money would come in
the debts would get paid off but that
over a course of years is not a good
business strategy at a certain point you
have to become realistic and we uh I
think that uh the buyer the principal
buyer was very enamored of the business
model and
overlooked that course of dealing by the
founders so I think uh
because it was such a relationship based
business and this middleman company
depended so heavily on the good graces
on the ability to negotiate preferable
rates with larger Logistics providers he
under our buyer underestimated the
importance of those key suppliers and
just thought the consent would be easier
to
get there's a couple a couple things I'd
love to learn more from you on on how
this went down so the two things that
jump out to me are of course the vendors
and creditors uh and also
negotiating uh with foreign cultures
whether it is abroad or you're dealing
with someone in the US because we do
have a lot of Israeli business owners
here that I'm sure would like to do
business the way that they are
accustomed to uh even living in the US
and you know even if you don't get
completely away from the US business
culture being respectful of you know
that sellers background can probably get
you more favorable terms uh so just with
the first question um when would you
recommend that a buyer talked to the uh
the vendors and creditors when should
they get that list and as an attorney
what are some of the best questions they
can ask to get the most accurate
information from a
seller I'd say you should be talking to
the people whoever they are if they're
creditors if they're shareholders
there's going to be a fly mment
somewhere you're going to need some
third party to consent so you need to
identify those third parties pre-
diligence I'd say pre-signing Loi if
possible but if not then in post Loi you
want to know the balance sheet in and
out you need to know as as soon as that
Loi is signed who you need to go to in
terms of a third party to get them
comfortable with this deal so as soon as
possible figure out who your sticking
points are going to be and and start
going after their consent and building a
relationship with them because you're
probably going to have to deal with them
in some capacity whether it's a you know
minority shareholder or really vocal
vendor or whatever you're going to have
to deal with them after the deal so as
soon as possible gotcha and for for our
listeners the Lo is a letter of intent
that's the uh the initial outline of the
terms of the deal and uh and Tom correct
me if I'm wrong this this sounds like it
applies to stock or asset purchases is
that right 100% yeah when you're talking
about stock purchases you're frequently
going to have to talk to a minority
shareholder or your round of investors
that would be converted automatically by
the terms of your investment or the
buyout usually when you sell a majority
of assets or shares in a company there
have to be some or there are going to be
some triggers for earlier investors to
either get paid out or to get stock in
the remaining entity obviously differs
between llc's and corpse assets versus
share deals but there are going to be
some triggers in there that you're going
to have to account for right so vendors
and creditors always always a checklist
item you have to hit and early and
that's it's kind of a you know I see two
two two themes here which is one I think
it's a success story for our Law Firm
because you know you provided a ton of
value I could see that deal going
through un lawyered or under lawyered
and them not you know being told don't
worry about the vendors they're fine we
have a great relationship with our
Logistics suppliers that's it's a joke
because we hear that all the time I have
a great relationship with the landlord I
have a great relation and you're I mean
so people tell me that and they don't
you know they don't understand I've
heard that four times that day and it's
never once been true so yeah we have a
great relationship with the logistics
provider and you can work it out after
closing with them um you can definitely
see that happening and then that person
the buyer effectuating the deal and
tanking immediately because he assumed
that once he was in control he could
work something out and that was not ever
going to happen so it's a success story
even though it didn't go through closing
because you know Tom was was able to
isolate hey we need these third party
consents and we're going to have to work
them out um now so that we know what
that looks like and um it's also one of
the reasons that uh a lot of
intermediaries say lawyers kill deals
because you know like yes true that is
one of the ones that you could have gone
through closing and then tanked and um
our job is to not let that happen so at
what point during the diligence process
did did this come up
Tom the third part of consent so the
first thing so when you when I get a a
letter of intent signed and then I
started thinking about how to structure
the purchase first thing I do is create
a checklist and in that checklist
there's a little box for a third party
consent that you fill in so as soon as
we got that Loi signed I went down the
list and said here are the people that
need consent based on the balance sheet
based on the structure of the company so
I told them immediately that these
people are going to have to consent I
always defer to my buyers if they say
I'm going to handle getting these
people's consent because it's not the
best and highest use of my time to be on
the phone with a bank and try to
negotiate commercial terms or the payoff
terms I can paper it and I'm happy to be
in the background there but ultimately
it's a business deal as to how they want
to compromise the way this debt goes
away and the way the consent gets
secured so it should be one of the first
things that you do any big law first
year to third year m&a associate third
party consents that's what you're put on
you're at the bottom of the checklist
and you are just sending polite reminder
emails every week hello what is the
status of our third party consent I have
drafted this consent form please sign
this consent form hello I'm not going
away in a very friendly way but it's
just it's not glamorous and it's such a
basic part of deals but I think that in
a smaller firm if you don't have that
training those consents are easy to lose
track of and just presume that they're
going to show up at the end of the deal
and a lot of times they do and if you're
a buyer who's taking advantage of SBA
you're doing a sub5 million deal that
means that there probably isn't that uh
that associate that's that's sending
those reminders for you so that means
buyer you're doing it yourself so don't
forget that is one of your jobs when
you're buying your own deal especially
in a smaller small business acquisition
that is very true and it I mean don't
take anyone's word for it I can't tell
you how many times everybody thinks it's
going to go great because they're told
there should be no problem and so they
wait until it it's usually at my urging
when I'm helping uh uh when we're
helping folks out we're pushing for it
you know we're trying we're not going to
let it close without those consents um
so the worst case scenario I describ in
the Israeli deal of it closing and then
them realizing that they would have
basically no functional business us um
that's not going to really happen
hopefully cuz we're going to make you
get them but it will slow your deal down
and that will potentially kill a deal
and anger everyone because you were
supposed to get these third party
consents you assumed it would be no
problem maybe even the seller doesn't
want you to talk to the people because
they you know they want to have a
certain level of shess that the deal is
going to go through before they tell
they're like vendors or important third
parties or landlord whoever um
you understand that reason that would be
they don't want to like wave the flag
that they're trying to sell before it's
true so they'll wait until the very end
and then there will be this big Hiccup
and it slows everything down or turns it
all the way upside down so with this
being an attorney heavy episode let's
let's do a Redemption Arc and uh let's
save some deals for all the deals killed
by
attorneys how how else would you learn
about negotiating with folks of of other
cultures whether they're in the US or
outside of the US if not from your
experts so Tom I love the fact that you
took that extra step to go and research
negotiating with different cultures what
did you find uh you know how how would
you recommend that a buyer approach a
seller who you know they if they know
where they're from how can they respect
that culture and and use that in
business and and do you have any
resources that you would recommend from
your recent
research there are a bunch of books
written on different negotiating Styles
and different cultures also obviously I
just learned by Googling it but the the
important thing is to realize that
you're not taking crazy pills and
neither is the other side it just people
have their habits and if you don't
figure out what those habits are ask
questions about them and establish a
working relationship before the first
sign of conflict that's when it can go
sideways so no matter what the the the
culture is say just take the initiative
to learn about it this homework has
definitely been done before I remember
negotiating with Chinese suppliers when
I was in house and you would talk about
everything but the deal that you you
didn't mention the deal you would go to
these dinners you would have a great
time and at some point the next morning
an email would come through with a hint
of a deal point and then once that
working relationship had been
established once everybody knew where
everybody stood then the business deal
could kind of get done and then it was
shuffled off to the attorneys to paper
it and I'm used to saying all right
we're we're here for business we're
going to talk about business let's get
into it but that's not the way it goes
so for Israel I I would say that I
wasn't prepared for the emotions that
came with it I wasn't prepared for the
cultural significance of what the
founders had done and I didn't fully
appreciate it and bring it to the buyer
attention and say I don't think these
people are going to budge I think they
mean what they say and so a certain
amount of brinksmanship is what we're
paid to deal with as attorneys but
culturally what brinksmanship means
differs so I would say if you're
encountering resistance the reason for
that resistance is not culturally
uniform and you should try to dig deeper
there I love that I mean we talk about
deals that don't make it to the closing
table or deals that are a struggle to
get to the closing table but so many
deals so many businesses fall apart in
the preceding 12 to 18 months after
closing and part of that businesses tend
to liver die based on the transition and
if you are just a bull in the china shop
with a seller especially around their
cultural expectations for a negotiation
doing a business deal that's really
going to lay the groundwork for the
relationship you have working with them
for the next 12 months so it's a
valuable piece to uh really lean on
prioritize and it should be fun too
right because it's different it it gives
you something else in your little
toolkit and if nothing it gives you kind
of a fun story at the end although I
would have preferred this deal had gone
through it's just economically if we had
paid every creditor we couldn't have
earned through the uh the hit that the
balance sheet would have taken to make
it a profitable business along the
returns required for that buyer's model
and you got to be honest with the model
at the end of the day you're modeling is
certain return and especially with PE
you've got to um those returns are taken
seriously because they've got to go to
their LPS a little bit more flexible
obviously with a smaller buyer in an SBA
deal well I think you know what you're
highlighting and I think I've talked
about in past episodes maybe uh the
cultural difference between kind of Wall
Street and Main Street the private
Equity folks uh who are buying just
regular people's businesses that they
built and there is a culture Clash a lot
of times there um
even if they're the exact same type of
person living in the exact same city
they're coming from really different
angles but one of the things that is
unusual in your example that probably
you could extrapolate to others is PE
those folks have fiduciary obligations
to their investors and they're reporting
back so they can't um make decisions
purely On Emotion um in the same way
that other uh people can um because and
maybe that's a cultural shift for
Israeli folks too I don't know what
their law is related to you know um
Executives at a business and whether
they have to you know make the best and
highest decisions for their investors in
the same way we have that you know rule
of law in the United States um but it
seems like maybe they didn't because
they would rather have zero dollars and
see a company fail and have some dollars
and in the United States um most people
could really really really detest a
business and still take the Pennies on a
dollar choice because they would feel
like they were obligated to their
investors to do that um so knowing that
it they don't have any obligation
flowing back is really valuable it
changes their decisions entirely that's
the same thing you have when you have a
business owner who doesn't have any
investors who's looking at a PE buyer
they've got different rules of the
road and and I want to add a qualifier
here because I have an N of one and a
half on deals in Israel so I can't say
that I'm you know source of Truth here
but that was definitely something I
noticed and it was confirmed by the
research I
did so as we come up on the end of the
episode I we have a unique opportunity
here it wasn't planned so Sarah doesn't
know about this either but uh we have a
great time a great opportunity with the
two of you to talk about Partnerships
and we don't have to like go deep into
it but so many people who are looking to
go out and buy a business on their own
uh maybe they've never worked with
someone maybe they've never been an
entrepreneur before they've never had a
business partner and U as a professional
especially from my time in accounting
I've seen countless Partnerships go
horribly horribly wrong how do you find
a good partner and then run a successful
partnership for five years oh
gosh Sarah you want to take first
cut oh man well uh I think I would be
very reticent to get into business with
anyone but Tom at this point in my life
I you know I think um for everybody that
wants to start a business call Tom yeah
call Tom get in line because um you know
there there's uh in a best partnership
you have uh
complimentary traits and I feel like uh
Tom's traits compliment mine very very
well so when we're working together on
the same deal um you know I'm uh a lot
uh how would you describe it
Tom you know people and deal with people
very well I am I would say more logical
and less emotionally oriented and you
shine in that realm you shine connecting
people and it's something I admire about
you and try to learn from but you know I
mean I can and Tom has this know his
stick tutiven this um academic strength
that is also just so unwavering so he
can't be pushed around at all um which
is fantastic so the combination is
perfect um but we got lucky there and um
I don't know it maybe a little bit of
how I met Tom was probably like a good
precursor to why we work well together
cuz he was kind enough to put up with
with me but um I applied for the same
in-house job that he ultimately got so
we had never met each other and then um
I just followed the the employer and
waited till they advertised who got the
job and then when they did
I uh dm'd him on LinkedIn and was like
can I buy you a beer and then just spent
the whole time trying to figure out why
he was better than
me I was like who is this crazy person
at LinkedIn tried to buy me beer so I
went in with walls up what and what
Sarah didn't know is that I just had m&a
on my resume and that was the only
reason I got the job otherwise she would
have blown me out of the water in an
interview it was great no and he was
great at it and then ultimately we
became friends because he was kind
enough to put up with whatever that was
and uh and then uh ultimately he came
and left that in-house position to come
and start this with uh me so you know we
won and and their loss but um he you
know he put up with that he is a very
loyal determined friend um so I think
that that makes it work well but I do
usually dissuade people from getting
into business with other folks because I
don't think it usually works out too
good well I love that hustle and taking
the initiative to reach out to uh to to
the person who defeated you and uh and
buying him a beer that was a that was a
great move
thanks from my side yeah everything that
Sarah said but I think that we had a a
nice soft launch because before we
started working together we'd
established trust and we'd also I think
crucially shared what our aspirations
were in an unfiltered way because when
we shared them there was nothing to be
gained or lost by either party and so
once we figured out that we had the same
dream of the lifestyle we wanted to live
we'd had similar big firm experiences we
could trust that we wanted to take it in
roughly the same direction and what I
always tell folks is don't work with
people that you don't trust and don't be
in the same business but uh pursuing
different dreams for that business they
don't have to be identical but they
should be
complimentary so got it uh and the last
thing is try to work with people who do
the things that they do for similar
reasons uh that you do the things that
you do so Sarah and I are lawyers
because we enjoy it we enjoy the
challenge we enjoy the connection we
enjoy the problem solving we don't enjoy
it because of the money we don't enjoy
because of uh getting to tell people
that we're lawyers yeah sometimes it's
nice but there are a material percentage
of lawyers out there who don't practice
for the same reasons and if you're
working your butt off and you're pouring
your life into something for or with
somebody that doesn't share your dream
or uh your motivation then there's going
to be a problem that's awesome so I hear
complimentary skills values alignment
trust and something that I see is that
it sounds like you just keep
complimenting each other and you'll
probably go pretty
far it's easy to talk to Tom because he
is very direct too so I think if you can
communicate easily to somebody uh you're
you're in a good start for sure um I
feel like I could say anything
immediately that I thought to Tom
without having to you know stress or
couch it and soften it
or yeah awesome I completely agree we
know who each other are and we we trust
and respect that well before we wrap up
Tom what is your specialty how can
people work with you how do you want
people to reach
you well specialty is deals uh we've
been getting into more financial
services deals lately I also do some
Outsource general counsel work which
kind of comes generally from working
with companies uh acquires but also
sellers cleaning things up for for sale
how can people get in touch with me uh
we've got a website SK ands legal.com or
you can email me at codilla skns
legal.com I'm not even going to try to
spell that because it's extremely long
and people usually hear the V and my
name is the Z so uh we will send out the
contact information with the episode I
think yeah it'll be in the the show
notes it'll be in the description uh
we'll make sure people can can get that
email address and your website to to get
in touch uh certain deal size certain
industry anything like that someone
should be thinking about if they're
going to reach out to you I'd say my
deals are split pretty evenly between
SAS manufacturing and financial services
deal size uh anywhere from a million to
I think the largest deal I've done is
about
35 40 million u in as a as skns uh
partner so pretty broad range but I'd
say The Sweet Spot is in the2 to10
million range fantastic Sarah closing
statements before we wrap it up oh
thanks Tom for coming and giving us such
a good example of why it's important to
get those third party consense it was
nice to see you good to see you too
thanks for having me on so this has been
episode four with Tom codilla at
skns Law law group yep longer wow I
should know that I
apologize uh all right episode 4 and
that's a w thanks so much uh if you like
this episode you got some value like And
subscribe leave a comment tell us what
you want to know if you have any
additional questions we'll make Tom come
back all right see you next
time
brother do it biger than anybody